Connectivity and New Account Creation

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

You can connect to the Grex server and create a new account, or login with your existing loginID and password, using the following programs:

Internet Browser - easy, secure, with limited access to Grex services unless you have Java (JRE) installed
SSH - easy, secure, complete; may require extra configuration

After UNIX account creation you need to validate your account - this is an extra step designed to prevent abuse. Type: validate and follow the instructions provided.

Internet Web Browser Access

Use our web based account creation link to create a new account. Note: our web based account creation software is not ready at this time. The link will take you to instructions for using ssh to set up an account.

You can access the Grex BBS by clicking on Backtalk - Agora is our frequently read conference (forum).

If you want complete access to Grex using a web browser you need to install Java (JRE - Java Runtime Environment). You can then access the Grex Unix shell by clicking on the MindTerm applet link within your browser - a Java applet (program) called MindTerm is loaded by your web browser. This Java-applet is used by your browser to connect to our Grex server's SSH port. If it doesn't work, read our troubleshooting Grex connectivity page.

SSH Access

SSH is a program for making secure connections to remote, terminal-oriented services. It encrypts the data sent between it and a remote server (such as Grex), and is capable of authenticating users using public key encryption. Using SSH in one form or another is the only way to get interactive access to Grex's shell services.

Windows 2000, Windows XP

A default Windows installation does not come with a free SSH client program - a free program that does SSH can be found on Simon Tatham's PuTTY page. Download this to your Desktop and double click it to run.
Host Name (or IP address) is grex.org. Click: Open to connect to Grex.

Unix, Linux, and Mac OS X

At a shell prompt, type: ssh newuser@grex.org
ssh jbrown@grex.org

Sample SSH output

        localhost> ssh newuser@grex.org
        The authenticity of host 'grex.org (216.86.77.194)' can't be established.
        RSA key fingerprint is 75:cc:a7:b5:b8:6a:6a:cc:a6:71:20:8d:ed:df:62:72.
        Are you sure you want to continue connecting (yes/no)?
      

What you are seeing is a sample of the Grex server's SSH key fingerprint. Make sure what you see within your SSH window matches our current server-fingerprint.

Type yes and press Enter, if it matches. You will then be lead to SSH based, new user registration process. Follow the instructions to create your new account.

Telnet Access

Telnet usage has been removed from Grex as of October 10, 2011 due to security issues. We suggest you use SSH (see above).

$Id: connect.xhtml 1448 2014-03-23 20:15:37Z kentn $ We welcome your feedback.

Grex Contact Information

Grex has numerous contact addresses. It is important to use the right one, because that way your question will be directed to the right group of people. This will save time for everyone concerned. Please take the time to determine the correct contact address.

Access Problems

If you are having access problems, such as an invalid or lost password, send email to staff, at help@grex.org.

Reporting Abuse

If you received an abusive or other unwanted e-mail message or post from a Grex address, or if you wish to report any other kind of abusive behavior that involves Grex, please contact abuse@grex.org. Please note that if you are reporting abusive mail, you should forward the offending mail to this address and be sure to include full mail headers. (In Pine, the "h" command shows you these headers.)

Reporting Spam

We cannot promise to eliminate all unsolicited commercial email (U.C.E.) messages from reaching your Grex mailbox. However, we are interested in doing the best that we can to reject such "spam" because we do not consider it to be an appropriate use of Grex's resources. If you receive any such messages in your Grex mailbox, you may report these by sending a message to uce@grex.org. Please attach a copy of the offending message, and include full mail headers. (In Alpine, the "h" command shows you these headers.)

Mail Administration

All questions or reports of problems relating to mail on Grex (except for reports of abusive or unwanted mail) should be sent to the Grex postmaster, postmaster@grex.org.

Conference Administration

The conference administrators are responsible for maintaining the proper functioning of the Grex conferences, and for creating new conferences. Please use cfadm@grex.org to communicate with the conference administrators.

Party Administration

The party program is Grex's real-time chat facility. there is a separate group of administrators for party. These people are responsible for maintaining channels and other party features. Please contact partyadm@grex.org.

Web Server Administration

Grex's web site is maintained by a separate group of staff members. If you have questions or suggestions about the web site, if you want to be listed in Grex's index of users' pages, or if you are having problems with the server, please contact the Grex Webmasters, at webmaster@grex.org.

The Grex Staff

Grex is maintained by an all-volunteer staff. If you have any general questions about Grex, about your account, or anything not explicitly listed above, send it to the Grex staff, at help@grex.org.

Cyberspace Communications, Inc.

Grex is governed by Cyberspace Communications, Inc., a non-profit organization that was founded with the primary purpose of establishing and running Grex. The Cyberspace Communications board of directors is elected by the members of Grex. The board can be reached by email at board@grex.org or by mail at

Cyberspace Communications, Inc.
P.O. Box 4432
Ann Arbor, MI 48106-4432
USA

$Id: contact.xhtml 1416 2014-03-23 00:40:30Z kentn $ We welcome your feedback.

Frequently Asked Questions About Grex

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

Table of Contents

General

What is Grex?
What does the name "Grex" mean?
What can I do on this system?
What operating system are you running?

Conferencing

What is "computer conferencing?"
How can I participate in Grex's conferences?

Governance

How is Grex governed?
How can I participate in Grex governance?
Can I pay for membership by credit card?

How do I...?

... change my name, my shell, my mail forwarding or my password?
... change my login ID?
... set up a web page?
... run irc?
... chat with others?
... get out of vi?
... access Usenet news?
... run X-windows?
... restore a lost file from a backup tape?
... get a list of Unix commands?
... use Unix commands?
... access Web-based mail providers?

Accounts and Passwords

I can't remember my password. What do I do?
I have a Grex account. Why do I get "No such loginid?"
I don't want to use my account anymore. How do I get it deleted?
When I enter my password, why don't I see anything?

E-Mail

How do I get Grex to forward my mail to another site?
I set up .forward myself. Why doesn't it work?
How can I hide my forwarding address?
How do I read mail with a browser or email client like Thunderbird or Outlook?
My mailbox is getting heavily spammed. What can I do?
Why is mail that I send to Grex getting rejected?
Can I configure my mail program to save outgoing mail?
Can I send attachments?
How can I view an attachment file named myfile.doc?
How can I set the "From" header in alpine for my outgoing mail?
How do I set up a mailing list here?
Is it OK to collect my mail by FTP?
Why can't I get procmail to work?
Can I set up an autoresponder to answer my mail while I am away for a while?

Privacy, Encryption, and Security

My personal information should be private. Why is it shown?
How can I keep private the place I'm logged on from?
I am receiving unwanted chat requests. What can I do?
How can I view my friend's files?
Can I run GPG or PGP on Grex to protect my email messages from being seen by others?
Do you provide secure shell?
Do you allow Grex to be used as a proxy for SSH?
What is Grex's SSH fingerprint, so I can be sure I'm connecting to the real Grex?

Programming

How do I compile a program?
I compiled my program. Why won't the system run it?
Can I have a copy of Grex's write/chat/tel programs?
Can I have a copy of Grex's party program?
Please install Java?

Miscellaneous

What is Grex's IP address?
Why does the "who" command show numeric IP addresses for some users?
Why does my browser say "Can't find application" when I click on the "SSH In" link?
When I try to SSH to Grex, it hangs. Why can't I connect?
I can't connect to the Mindterm terminal. What do I need to do?
Can I do a ping or traceroute from Grex?
How much disk space can I use and how can I determine how much I am using?
Why doesn't my arrow key work, so I can edit previous commands in sh?
Why can't I edit previous commands in tcsh, ksh, or bash? They are supposed to support it.
Why does the last line of each page of text disappear from the screen before I can read it?
Why do the bottom lines stay on the screen in the editor while the rest scroll normally?
Why doesn't "screen" work when I disconnect from Grex?
I found a huge core file in my account. What should I do?
How does the system decide where to put my home directory?
Where can I get a self-contained multi-user chat program for my linux box?
How can I get colors in the output from "ls"?
I know something about Unix. How can I help the Grex staff?

General

What is Grex?

Grex is a public-access Unix system providing free shell accounts and a computer conferencing community. It is based out of the United States. It is cooperatively owned and operated, and is supported entirely by user donations and volunteers.

What does the name Grex mean?

Grex is not an acronym. It is a Latin word meaning flock. It is the root of a number of familiar English words such as aggregate, congregate, and gregarious.

What can I do on this system?

Grex provides all of the following services for free.

Interactive Unix shell access, and access to the standard suite of Unix software including shells, tools and document preparation software.
An interactive software development environment supporting many languages, compilers, editors, interpreters and tools.
A number of software packages of mathematical, scientific, and statistical processing.
Internet email using "mail", "mutt", "alpine" or "mh"
Browse the web in text mode using "links", "w3m" or "lynx"
Access to IRC
Access to USENET
Access to SSH, scp, sftp, and ftp to connect to other systems and services
Free web site hosting
On-line games, including "Nethack"
Electronic conferencing using "Backtalk" or "Fronttalk"
Multichannel real-time chat using "party"

Please note that you must be a validated user to use software anything related to the network.

And there are a few things you can only do if you are a member (who has made a donation and sent ID). These are

Vote in Grex elections.
Serve on the board of Cyberspace Communications.

What operating system is Grex running?

Grex is currently running a nearly stock version of OpenBSD.

For the first 13 years of it's life, Grex ran on second-hand Sun computers, using Sun's proprietary version of Unix. However, Grex now runs on standard server hardware based on the Intel 386 instruction set.

There are a lot of details about Grex's configuration available in the Grex staff notes on the web. Follow this link to more information about Grex's Hardware and software.

Conferencing

What is "computer conferencing?"

A computer conference is an area set aside for discussion on some general topic, such as computers, politics, or gardening. In such an area, people can read what other people have posted, and can introduce new subtopics or add responses to existing ones. On many systems, conferences are called "forums". Grex has many conferences. For a complete list, see https://grex.org/cgi-bin/backtalk/pistachio/conflist.

How can I participate in Grex's conferences?

Grex's conferences are accessible by a text-based terminal interface or by the World Wide Web. To access the text-based interface, SSH into Grex and run the "bbs" command. (This command is run automatically every time you log in if you choose the "bbs shell" after you validate your account.) World Wide Web access is provided by Grex's "Backtalk" conferencing software. Please see https://grex.org/cgi-bin/backtalk for details on using Backtalk.

Governance

How is Grex governed?

Cyberspace Communications functions as an online democracy, with policies set by its users. The Co-op Conference is open to all users and provides a forum for discussing policy issues. The Board of Directors, elected by the members, is the formal governing body and uses consensus in the Co-op Conference as its primary guide for making decisions. Any member of Grex who can attend the monthly meetings, held in Ann Arbor, Michigan, is eligible to run for the Board of Directors. In addition, any member can call a binding vote by the membership on any policy issue. The Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws can be viewed online.

How can I participate in Grex governance?

Any user can have a voice in Grex governance by joining the Co-op conference and participating in the discussions there. If you wish to be eligible to vote in Grex elections and to run for the Board of Directors, you can become a Grex member. Membership dues are US$2/month or US$18/year. To find out how to make membership payments, please see http://grex.org/member.xhtml. Membership donations are Grex's primary source of financing.

Can I pay for membership by credit card?

Yes!

How do I ... ?

How do I change my name, my shell, my mail forwarding or my password?

You can change any of these properties of your account with the "change" command. If you are using a menu or if you are at a bbs (Ok) prompt, type "!change" If you are in lynx, type "!" (an exclamation point) to get to a shell prompt first. At a shell prompt, type "change" and follow the menu-based instructions.

Note: For changing your shell, you will be put in the unix chsh command. The acceptable shells for this command are:

/bin/sh
/bin/csh
/bin/ksh
/usr/local/bin/bash
/usr/local/bin/es
/usr/local/bin/psh
/usr/local/bin/rc
/usr/local/bin/sash
/usr/local/bin/scsh
/usr/local/bin/tcsh
/usr/local/bin/zsh
/cyberspace/bin/bbsh
/cyberspace/bin/menu

How do I change my login ID?

You can't change it. Instead, you have to create a new account with the login ID that you wish. Once you have done that, you can copy the files that you need from your old account to your new one. When you no longer need your old account, you can ask to have it deleted by sending a request from your old account to help@grex.org.

How do I set up a web page?

There is a completely separate FAQ for all questions related to the Grex web server. Please see http://grex.org/wwwfaq.xhtml.

How do I access IRC?

If you are an unvalidated user, you cannot access IRC. We strongly urge you to get validated! Send email to porters@grex.org to get started! You must have a Grex user name in order to be validated. Please see http://grex.org/newuser/index.xhtml for instructions.

If you are a validated user, you can access IRC through a number of clients we have installed including the venerable ircII, the well-known irssi, sirc and several others.

Grex does not allow the running of bots or bouncers such as psybnc or eggdrop. They will be killed if found running. Persistent running of bots or bouncers may result in your account being locked.

How do I chat with others?

Grex has six ways of chatting:

'party' is a chat program that many people can run at once.
'write' sends text to the other person's screen one line at a time.
'chat' is like 'write' but it sends one character at a time.
'tel' is like 'write' but it sends only one line and then stops.
'talk' splits the screen in half, so both people can type at once.
'ytalk' is like talk but can accommodate more than two people.

How do I get out of vi?

vi (pronounced vee-eye) is a powerful text editor, but it has a steep learning curve at first. You can usually tell that you are in vi when you have a vertical line of squiggles (tildes) on the left of your screen. If you are trapped in vi, remember to type the escape key and then :q! (colon-q-exclamation point) followed by a return. The "ee" and "pico" editors are much friendlier for less experienced users.

How do I access Usenet news?

There are a number of Usenet reader programs on Grex, including slrn, tin, trn and nn. You can also access Usenet via one of the text web browsers installed on Grex, such as w3m, links or lynx. Just connect to http://groups.google.com/.

How do I run X11 programs?

The easiest way is to login to Grex using SSH, which will likely set your DISPLAY environment variable and X authority files automatically. Then, just run the graphical program in question. Alternately, you may have to specify these settings by hand; check the X11 documentation for more details.

Note, however, that using X from Grex is likely to be painfully slow, and also uses a lot of resources on Grex itself. We ask that, in general, you refrain from using X programs.

How do I restore a lost file from a backup

We can't do that. We just don't have time. Grex makes nightly backups, but the purpose of these backups is to protect the system from disaster. Unfortunately, there is not enough time to honor requests from individual users to restore files. Grex is not a good place to keep any file that you cannot afford to lose. If you have an important file on Grex, it is your responsibility to keep a backup of it on your own computer.

How do I get a list of Unix commands?

There are so many Unix commands that we recommend that users who are not familiar with Unix use the "menu" command to explore Grex. The most common commands are available there. If you really want a list, then run the Grex command "listcommands" to print a list of most Unix commands on Grex. (Built-in shell commands are not included). This will take a long time to run.

How do I use Unix commands?

The Unix operating system is amazingly powerful and flexible, with thousands of commands. Unix can be a challenge to get started with, but if you are interested in learning Unix, Grex is a good place to start, since we do give you access to almost all commands.

For online introductions to basic Unix commands and editors such as emacs and vi usage, consult Google and do searches for things like, Unix tutorial or vi tutor.

Online reference information about most commands can be called up via the "man" command. For example, for information about the date command, type:

man date

The book Unix for the Impatient is excellent, though slightly dated.

How do I access Web mail?

You can try with one of the textual browsers installed on Grex, but most web-based mail services expect graphical browsers with more functionality. However, you can use some webmail servers (for instance, GMail) by configuring one of the mail programs already installed on Grex (for instance, mutt or alpine) to pull mail via POP3 or IMAP from a remote server and to send outgoing mail through a remote server.

Accounts and Passwords

I can't remember my password. What do I do?

Contact the Grex staff. Send mail from another site if you have access to email at another site. Send messages about access problems to help@grex.org. Remember to specify which account is the one you lost the password for.

You can also log in to Grex as "trouble" without a password, which will send a message to the staff. Be sure to provide a postal address, an email address, or a local telephone number, so that the staff can contact you in return.

I have a Grex account. Why do I get "No such loginid?"

This means that your account has been deleted. Accounts on Grex are deleted if no one logs in for more than 3 months. There is not enough room on Grex to keep old unused accounts. To avoid losing your account, you should log in every month or two. Accessing your web page, or having your mail get forwarded does not count, but conferencing over the web using your account and password in Backtalk does count as logging in for this purpose.

If your account has been deleted, it usually cannot be recovered or restored. Please feel free to recreate the account.

I don't want to use my account anymore. How do I get it deleted?

If you don't want to wait until your account expires, you have to log in one last time and send a message to help@grex.org from the account that you want deleted. In your message, ask for it to be deleted.

When I enter my password, why don't I see anything?

Grex does not display your password as you type it. This is to keep it secret from anybody who might be looking over your shoulder. Type your password anyway. Even though you don't see it, Grex will register it and, if you typed it correctly, you will be logged in.

Email

How do I get Grex to forward my mail to another site?

Put the address to which you would like your Grex email forwarded to in a file called ".forward" in your home directory.

If you don't know how to do that, you can use the "change" command. Just type "change" at a shell prompt or "!change" at any other prompt. This will invoke a menu that allows you to change common setting for your account, including the mail forwarding option.

I set up .forward myself. Why doesn't it work?

Probably because it is not world readable. .forward files must be world readable in order to be valid on Grex. If you are looking for a way to forward your mail to an anonymous place, you need to find an anonymous remailer system. Grex doesn't do this. To make your .forward file world readable, change to your home directory (type: cd) and then issue this command:

chmod 644 .forward

Your home directory must also be world accessible; type:

chmod 755 .

or use 711 instead of 755 if you don't want other people to be able to scan your directory.

How can I hide my forwarding address?

You can't. Grex does not wish to provide anonymous remailing services. You may wish to make use of one of the various anonymous remailers available on the Internet; use your favorite web search engine to find one.

How do I read mail with Thunderbird or Outlook?

Configure your local client to connect to Grex via SSL encrypted IMAP and SMTP; enter your grex login name and password where prompted.

Please note, we support the IMAP protocol, but not POP3.

My mailbox is getting heavily spammed. What can I do?

Spam (unwanted mail) is unfortunately very common on the internet, and there's little anyone can do about it.

Grex has installed SpamAssassin to help you cut down on the noise. This reduces but does not eliminate spam.

Why is mail that I send to Grex getting rejected?

This usually happens when the sending site is not configured properly. Problems in mail configuration can often lead to mail that has an invalid return address. Grex's mail system tries very hard to detect and reject invalid sending addresses, in order to reduce the amount of spam on Grex. If your mail looks like spam, then Grex will reject it. If you think this is happening to your legitimate mail, send a rejected copy of it to help@grex.org, and be sure to include all of the mail headers. Ordinarily, the additional surrounding text and context of the forwarded email should be enough to convince the mailer that the email is legitimate.

Other common reasons for mail to Grex to be rejected are that it may be too large or your mailbox may have grown too large.

Can I configure my mail program to save outgoing mail?

This feature is turned off on Grex by default, because lots of new users were accumulating vast files of old mail without ever knowing that they were doing it. You're quite welcome to configure this feature, as long as you keep an eye on your disk usage so that you don't exceed Grex's 100 megabyte limit for your account.

To configure your mail client, consult its documentation. For alpine, go into the configuration screen and look for the setting for "default-fcc". Set it to "saved-mail" or whatever name you would like to use. You need to use quotation marks around the file name.

Can I send attachments?

Yes. You must first transfer the file you wish to attach to Grex, and then attach it when composing your email message. If you don't need the file on Grex after you've sent it, please remember to delete the file after you are done. Also, please keep attachments to a reasonable size so as not to overwhelm our service.

How can I view an attachment file named myfile.doc?

Any file that ends with ".doc" is probably a Microsoft Word file. There is no way to view such a file on Grex. You will have to download that file to a computer that has Microsoft Word or some other word processor that can import such files.

How can I set the "From" header in pine for my outgoing mail?

In Pine on Grex, you can't set the "From:" field. This is disabled because there were too many problems with people setting invalid addresses, which caused their outgoing mail to bounce to the postmaster whenever it was undeliverable.

How do I set up a mailing list here?

You can't. We're sorry, but this is not permitted. You can only forward mail to a single site elsewhere on the internet. Mailing lists are too resource intensive for Grex to support. You may wish to try using an advertising-based free mailing list service. Both Google Groups and Yahoo Groups offer free mailing lists with lots of features.

Is it OK to collect my mail by SCP, SFTP or FTP?

Yes, but you must do it correctly.

It is risky to attempt to transfer your mail spool file off of Grex. You risk losing some or all of your collected mail, because the sftp, scp and FTP daemons does not participate in the locking scheme used by the mail delivery programs. In addition, your account may appear to be abandoned because file transfers do not update the date of last login. This could result in loss of your account if it is the only way you use Grex.

Instead, we recommend connecting to Grex and running a mail client program. These all do participate in the locking mechanism for the mail spool. Collect all of your mail into a file in your home directory, and then log out. You may now safely fetch that file, but please remember to delete it once it has been safely transferred.

Why can't I get procmail to work?

The most likely reason is that you have not told procmail how to find your mail spool file. To find your spool file, type

echo $MAIL

Procmail will work if you make this one of the first lines of the .procmailrc file:

MAIL=PATH-TO-YOUR-INBOX

For example, the first line of a .procmailrc file used by member John Remmers (remmers) would be:

MAIL=/var/mail/remmers
Can I set up an autoresponder to answer my mail while I am away for a while?

Yes. Try the vacation program. Type vacation to run it.

Privacy, Encryption, and Security

My personal information should be private. Why is it shown?

When you look up your own user information, you can always see it, even if it is set up so that nobody else on the system can see it. To see what other people see, ask for the info about "youraccount@grex.org" instead of just "youraccount".

How can I keep private the place I'm logged on from?

This is considered public information on Grex. The only way to hide it is not to log on.

I am receiving unwanted chat requests. What can I do?

You can adjust the chat settings for your account with the "change" command. To run it, type "change" at a shell prompt, or "!change" from a menu or from bbs. Then choose "W) Write settings" and follow the menus from there. You can: turn off all chat requests, accept all chat requests, or select which users can and cannot chat with you.

How can I view my friend's files?

Grex is a very open system, so directories are open to the public unless the owner decides to make them private. Email, however, is automatically saved in private files that the world cannot see.

To permit a file so that it can be seen by others, type

chmod a+r file-name

To permit a directory, type

chmod a+rx dir-name

To hide a file or directory, type

chmod ou-rx file-or-dir-name

If you hide your home directory completely, neither mail forwarding nor web hosting will be available to you. You may make your directory accessible without allowing it to be scanned. This is how:

chmod 711 dir-name

Can I run PGP on Grex to protect my email messages from being seen by others?

Yes. PGP is available on Grex, but be aware that will probably not offer you the protection you seek on our service. In order to be effective, PGP must be installed on your own computer, not on Grex, which you should not consider secure. Encrypting or decrypting a message on Grex would mean that the message would have to travel over an insecure network before encryption or after decryption, and this is not the way to protect your message. Even if you connect to Grex using SSH, there is still a huge risk that Grex itself will be compromised.

In order to install PGP on your home computer, North American users should go to the MIT PGP Distribution Site at http://web.mit.edu/network/pgp.html, and all other users should use the international PGP home page at http://www.pgpi.org/.

Do you provide secure shell?

Yes, we do. Secure shell (ssh) is a good way to connect because your session is encrypted, so that passwords cannot be intercepted by sniffers. In fact, we have removed telnet access in favor of SSH in October 2011 due to these security concerns.

Do you allow Grex to be used as a proxy using SSH?

Sorry, no. This type of connection is disallowed by our firewall settings, so it won't work.

What is Grex's SSH fingerprint so I can be sure I'm connecting to the real Grex?

Currently Grex's SSH fingerprint is (depending on how SSH is connecting):

256 30:82:50:ba:6c:26:68:01:52:64:dc:54:83:8e:95:7e root@grex.cyberspace.org (ECDSA)
2048 2f:26:4a:b5:f3:df:85:e0:30:d1:94:3d:06:8e:be:66 root@grex.cyberspace.org (DSA)
2048 75:cc:a7:b5:b8:6a:6a:cc:a6:71:20:8d:ed:df:62:72 root@grex.cyberspace.org (RSA)
2048 79:b0:32:79:b5:a7:e2:67:d5:78:4e:27:d5:f3:62:c7 root@grex.cyberspace.org (RSA1)

Programming

How do I compile a program?

To compile a C program named foo.c, type gcc foo.c -o foo This compiles foo.c and creates an executable program named foo. To run it, type ./foo Likewise, to compile a C++ program named foo.cpp, type g++ foo.cpp -o foo Please check with the Grex staff before compiling programs you bring in from the net. Most of the useful programs are already installed here, and many others will not run on Grex, but compiling them on Grex wastes a lot of bandwidth and cpu time — resources that Grex is short on.

I compiled my program. Why won't the system run it?

Usually this is because the program is not on your path. Unlike a DOS or Windows system, on Unix the current directory is not automatically placed on your path. So if you compile a program named foo, you cannot run it by just typing "foo". You need either to place the executable somewhere on your path, or to precede its name with ./ (dot-slash) so you would type "./foo".

Can I have a copy of Grex's write/chat/tel programs?

Yes, you can find out more about write/chat/tel, including availability, on this web page: http://unixpapa.com/write.html.

Can I have a copy of Grex's party program?

Yes, you can find out more about party, including availability, on this web page: http://unixpapa.com/party.html.

Please install Java?

Java is installed on Grex. See: /usr/local/jdk-1.7.0/

Miscellaneous

Why does my browser say "Can't find application" when I click on the "SSH In" link?

You need to configure your browser to find your SSH application program. The exact instructions for doing this vary widely depending upon both your operating system and your browser. Select the SSH application that came with your system, or one you downloaded from the internet. For more details about SSH applications, see the Grex SSH Information page at http://grex.org/ssh.xhtml.

When I try to SSH to Grex, it hangs. Why can't I connect?

There are several things that can go wrong.

You don't have DNS working properly. In this case you can connect to Grex by using its IP address. See below.
You are accessing the net via a firewall which blocks SSH. In this case you need to contact your security administrator for the LAN which you are accessing the net from, and ask if there is a way to SSH through the firewall.
Your SSH client is not working properly. You would not be able to SSH to any other site, either. Have you tried any? Try connecting with SSH to arbornet.org and see if you get a login prompt.
Grex is down. This happens occasionally. You can usually tell if Grex is down by trying to access the web site. Try reloading to eliminate the possibility of a cached page. This won't be a good test if your connection uses a caching proxy server.
If it is none of the above, send mail to The Grex Staff and explain everything you tried, and also please specify the IP address and the GMT time that your attempt failed. If you can provide the results of a ping or traceroute from your end, that may prove to be helpful, too.

Can I do a ping or traceroute from Grex?

These tools are not available on Grex. Vandals were using them to attack other sites. This is a ludicrous thing to do from Grex, because Grex is so tiny that its CPU and net connection become overloaded long before any other system would even begin to notice that it was being attacked. But people were doing it anyway, and hurting Grex. Regrettably, the actions of a few thoughtless people has forced Grex to disable these potentially valuable network analysis tools.

You may be able to use a remote traceroute server on the web. See http://www.traceroute.org/.

What is Grex's IP address?

At the time this answer was last updated, the IP address of Grex was 162.202.67.158, but IP addresses may change at any time. In general, we have little control over changes to our IP address. You should always use the hostname, because if the IP address does change, the DNS (Domain/Name Service) lookup of the hostname should produce the new IP address. If you are unsure if a problem is due to DNS, you can test to see if you can connect using our IP address. However, if you can, it is strongly recommended that you resolve the problem you are having with DNS, so that you do not have to rely on inherently unreliable IP addresses.

Why does the "who" command show numeric IP addresses for some users?

That is because this information is stored in a file (utmp) which only permits 16 characters of storage for this information. If the IP address exceeds 16 characters when converted to text form, then it is stored (and reported) only in its numeric form. This affects other commands besides the "who" command, such as the "finger" and "last" commands.

How much disk space can I use and how can I determine how much I am using?

The disk quota on grex is 100 megabytes, enforced by the 'quota' system. You can find out how much disk space you are using (in kilobytes) by running the following command in your home directory:

du -sk

The number that comes back is the number of kilobytes of disk you are using. If you are using more than 100000, please remove files.

The command

quota

will show your quota and usage on the current file system. The command

quota -v

will show your quota and usage on all the file systems you have "write" access.

If you are thinking of putting something big in your account, please talk to the Grex staff (help@grex.org) first. There aren't many good reasons to put big things in your Grex account: Grex doesn't allow multimedia files on its web pages (not even image files), and most of the useful programs that will actually run on Grex are already installed on Grex. So please talk to the staff first.

If you exceed the 100 megabyte disk quota or have multimedia files, big downloaded program packages, or vandal tools, in your account, a member of the Grex staff will delete the files and quite likely lock your account. The Grex staff spent way too much time policing this and was usually quite crabby about the whole topic. So the current Grex computer has automated disk quotas, which will notify you when you go over quota and prevent your creating new files if you stay over quota.

Why doesn't my arrow key work, so I can edit previous commands in sh?

This is because Grex is running a real sh, and that is a feature not supported by sh. What some Unix systems call sh is actually bash, an enhanced version of the sh shell which does this. If you would like to use bash instead, you should change your shell on Grex to bash. You can do that by running the change command.

Why can't I edit previous commands in tcsh, ksh, or bash? They are supposed to support it.

Bash, ksh and tcsh do support previous line editing. It may not be working the way you expect because a different default editing mode is in use. To change the default editing mode to the style of emacs or vi, the command you must use depends upon your shell. For ksh and bash, use one of the following commands:

set -o emacs
set -o vi

The equivalents in tcsh are:

bindkey -e
bindkey -v

After that, you should be able to edit your command line in a way that is familiar to you. If you prefer to preserve this setting so you don't have to execute it every time you log in, then place it in .profile (ksh and bash) or .login (tcsh).

Why does the last line of each page of text disappear from the screen before I can read it?

This happens when Grex doesn't know how many rows of text are on your screen. The easiest way to set this correctly is to run the "resize" program on Grex. It will set things up for you.

Why do the bottom lines stay on the screen in the editor while the rest scroll normally?

Same problem. Wrong number of lines in the setting. See solution above.

Why doesn't "screen" work when I disconnect from Grex?

Grex runs a special daemon that kills all user processes when a user logs out. This prevents users from running servers or robots of any kind. It also prevents them from using the reconnect feature of screen (although the other features work fine). The reason for this policy is to prevent users from consuming our limited resources while not logged in.

Note: This was the case several years ago, but no longer is. screen should stay connected now.

I found a huge core file in my account. What should I do?

Nothing really. This is a file that gets created if a program fails (crashes). It is intended to help the programmer find whatever bug caused the failure. If not renamed, these files will be deleted automatically in a day or two. You can delete it if you wish. By the way, a core file usually doesn't take up as much space on the disk as it appears to, because it is "sparse" (full of empty space).

How does the system decide where to put my home directory?

Grex uses a hierarchical arrangement of home directories to keep the directory sizes from growing too large and thus becoming inefficient. So, on Grex, home directories are always located by a path of this form:

/x/y/z/username

The x is the disk letter, the y is the first letter of the username, and the z is the second letter of the username. Currently we have two disks that user accounts occupy, /a and /c (/b was not available). The choice of disk is determined when your account is created. This choice is switched back and forth manually by the staff to keep the available disk space balanced.

The environment variable $HOME should always be set to the full path of your home directory. The ~ symbol may also be used as a shorthand for your home directory, as long as your shell supports it. (The Bourne Shell does not.)

Where can I get a self-contained multi-user chat program for my linux box?

You might want to try out Grex's party program. See the Party Question in this FAQ.

How can I get colors in the output from "ls"?

Color listings are available with many terminal types, but whether or not they show up depends on which terminal emulator you're using. See http://grex.org/ssh.xhtml for more information on SSH programs. You also need to turn on color listing. This involves two steps. You will need to run gdircolors for you shell. If your shell is a sh-like shell (sh, bash, ksh), you will run the following command: eval `gdircolors -b` otherwise, if your shell is a csh like shell (csh, tcsh) you will run the following command: eval `gdircolors -c` Then, if you use ls with the --color=auto option, it will use colors. You can add the following alias to your .profile file of startup commands (for bash-type shells, or your .login file for csh-type shells): alias ls='/usr/local/bin/gls --color=auto' to always get color listings when your terminal emulator can support it.

I know something about Unix. How can I help the Grex staff?

We are always delighted to have new volunteers One of the things that Grex needs most urgently is more people to answer "help" requests. It is recommended that you check out the helpers conference.

Also you should read the Grex Staff Notes.

I can't connect to the Mindterm terminal. What do I need to do?

Mindterm is a java-based SSH terminal you can use from the Grex web site, so you need to have the Java Runtime Environment installed to use it. Make sure this is the case.

See Installing JRE

.

You will also need to add grex.org and cyberspace.org (and their related URLs with http:// and https://) to your Java Exception Site List. You do this from the Security tab in the Java Control Panel.

As Java and web browers get more and more particular about the sites they'll connect to, you may, from time to time, need to re-acknowledge and accept that you want to connect to grex.org.

$Id: faq.xhtml 1536 2015-12-29 17:05:52Z kentn $ We welcome your feedback.

What is Grex?

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

Grex is a public access Unix and computer conferencing system, featuring ongoing bulletin board discussion areas (called conferences), multi-user chat channels, Internet email, and more. Grex is supported by our users, and is run entirely by volunteers. Access is free, but donations are always welcome.

We're located in Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA, and have been running since 1991. Grex is owned by a non-profit corporation called Cyberspace Communications, Inc. But don't let the fancy name fool you - CCI has no employees or offices, and Grex is its main asset, aside from volunteers and users. If you become a member, you can vote in Grex elections, including the annual election for CCI's board of directors.

More about Grex:

Grex FAQ - Frequently Asked Questions about Grex.
User Guide - our online user's manual (a bit dated, but still useful.)
Staff Notes - Detailed descriptions of various adminstrative and technical matters from Grex's staff.
Cyberspace Communications - Our bylaws, monthly board meeting minutes, and more.
History of Grex - Background on our origins, excerpted from a conference discussion.
Declaration of Principles - A bit dry, but a good brief synposis of what Grex is about.
GrexWalk - Join Grexers for our weekly walk in Ann Arbor.
What's new on Grex? - A short list of recent changes to Grex.

$Id: grex.xhtml 1415 2014-03-23 00:37:47Z kentn $ We welcome your feedback.

Party on Grex

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

Party (party) is a multi-user chat program. Everything you type is shown on the screen of others who are running party. Everything they type is shown on your screen.

In order to use party, you must be logged in to Grex. There is no web-based chat service on Grex. If you are connecting over the internet, ssh to Grex. Note: this link will only work if your browser has been configured to start an SSH client (for example, there is an add-in for Firefox to allow this: FireSSH). If it doesn't work, you may need to change your browser's preferences, or in some cases, download an SSH client application program.

Once you are logged in, there are several commands related to party which you can use:

There is a FAQ which can be read by typing party-faq on the Unix command-line. You can also read the Unix documentation for party by typing man party
You can see who is in party at the moment by typing the pwho command.
Use the party command to start party. Type a ? to see what you can type, or just watch the conversation until you feel like joining in.

Party supports multiple channels, and has a "noise" feature which allows you to send canned responses with subtitutable strings.

If you have questions about party or wish to request some feature, please send e-mail to Grex's party admininstrators at partyadm@grex.org.

$Id: party.xhtml 1421 2014-03-23 00:54:40Z kentn $ We welcome your feedback.

SSH Information

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

What is SSH?

ssh (SSH client) is a program for logging into a remote machine and for executing commands on a remote machine. It is intended to replace telnet, rlogin and rsh, and provide secure encrypted communications between two untrusted hosts over an insecure network. Since your personal computer is not directly connected to our Grex server, the data you send us has to pass through unknown computers handling Internet data traffic. These machines have access and can read some of your transimitted data, if they choose. Your passwords and login info, among other things, could be stolen and, perhaps, used on other sites. SSH prevents all this by encrypting your transmitted data making it nearly impossible to understand.

How do I use SSH?

You need to download a program that supports the SSH protocol.

Most computers running Unix or its variants (including Mac OS X) already include an SSH client. Simply open a terminal or xterm window and type, "ssh your_login_name@grex.org".

You can download one such program for Microsoft Windows here. After downloading it to your Windows "Desktop", double click it to run. Our Host Name is: grex.org. Click the Open button and wait a few seconds for PuTTY to prompt you to accept our server's encryption key fingerprint. If the key you see in the PuTTY window is the same as the key on our website then click Yes. If you are creating a new user account, type newuser and follow the instructions provided. Else, type in your login and password.

What is Telnet?

Telnet programs are inherently insecure because they transmit unencrypted and easily readable data. Do not type in personal information (example: social security number) or financial data (eg: bank account details, password for a bank website) when using telnet. We no longer provide access via telnet.

Getting a Free SSH/Telnet Program

If you need to download and install an SSH program, the following programs are the ones that we recommend.

PuTTY (for all windows platforms)
PuTTY is a free implementation of Telnet and SSH for Win32 and Unix platforms, along with an xterm terminal emulator. It supports scp and sftp. If you are using a version of PuTTY earlier than 0.55, you should upgrade to 0.55. The latest version of PuTTY can be found at the author's website: http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/.
TeraTerm
TeraTerm is another free Windows-based SSH and Telnet program. More information can be found here.

$Id: ssh.xhtml 1444 2014-03-23 18:01:57Z kentn $ We welcome your feedback.

Putting Your Web Page on Grex

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

Grex provides limited web page hosting for anyone with a Grex account. Some of the more important limits are:

Limited data transfer capability; we are not Amazon-S3.
CGI and SSI support only if you write scripts that exit quickly and are not CPU intensive
Your pages are included in your 100 MB user space limit.
You still have to log in to your account every few months, in order to keep your account active.

You can get started by running the mkhomepage command at a shell prompt on Grex. This will create the necessary www directory, and place a prototype home page in index.html for you to edit.

There are many frequently asked questions about this service. Please read the WWW server FAQ before sending mail to webmaster@grex.org with questions you may have about this service.

Any Grex user who owns a web page, whether it is located on Grex or elsewhere, may have their site listed on our directory of Grex Users' Web Pages. Just send mail to webmaster and specify the account and (if the page is not on Grex) the URL.

Also, check out the Grex Web Server Statistics to see how many hits your page is getting. This is updated every week. For more information about the web server and webmasters, please follow this link

$Id: www.xhtml 1419 2014-03-23 00:50:37Z kentn $ We welcome your feedback.

Grex WWW FAQ

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

This is a compilation of questions frequently asked about web-based services on Grex.

Can I create a home page on Grex?
How do I get started?
What if I don't know HTML?
How many pages / how much space can I have in my website?
Why can't I find my page when I look from the net?
Why can't I edit my page using the "e" command in Lynx?
How can I put my pages on Grex if I make them on my computer?
Can I have HTML Forms on my page?
How do I get my page listed in the Grex Users directory?
If I have a page elsewhere, can I be listed on Grex?
How do I know how many "hits" my page is getting?
How can I put a counter on my page?
Can I put links to conference items on my page?
Help, I forgot my Grex password!

Can I create a home page on Grex?

Yes, Grex permits users to have free use of our web server under certain conditions.

We do not permit bandwidth intensive tasks

This generally involves downloading large amounts of GIF, JPEG, WAV, AU, AIFF, MPEG, MOV, and possibly other file formats.

We do not permit CPU intensive tasks

This means that you cannot write scripts, process forms, or implement gateways or counters, that hog the Grex processor.

No commercial use.

We do permit incidental commercial use such as an individual selling shareware, as long as it does not generate too much traffic.

There is a traffic limit due to our small link.

If activity on your site starts to approach 10 MB/day, we will ask you to look for another site or start paying. Our link can only stand so much. It is very slow. You will get plenty of warning in such an event.

No violation of copyright and pornography laws.

You must not break the laws of the United States of America. Grex will report any violations to the proper authorities with all details available to us (your name, address, files on Grex, IP address, etc)

In short: a user home-page with your resume and a few of your pics, music, programs and art-work, with a few friends and family visiting won't get you in any trouble with our staff.

Please note: we want to make Grex as useful to the general public as possible, but our activities are curtailed by resources available to us (money, staff time, volunteers). Please consider donating and volunteering to help with day to day activities.

Return to the table of contents

How do I get started?

First, you must create an account for yourself on Grex. Just SSH to Grex and log in as newuser, or else create your account on the web. You may also be able to use our MindTerm Java Client to connect from a web browser.

Once you have your account, and you can log in to Grex via SSH, then you run the mkhomepage program. This program gives you the option of creating a prototype home page. If your shell is not a unix shell, you must type a !mkhomepage in order to run it.

Return to the table of contents

What if I don't know HTML?

If you don't know HTML, you are not going to be able to write a web page. HTML is the language used to produce web documents, and no one is going to convert your documents to HTML for you.

Fortunately, it is rather simple to learn the basics of HTML, and there is a wealth of information on the net. Just do a few searches for HTML Tutorial to get started.

Return to the table of contents

How many pages / how much space can I have in my website?

You can put any pages that you wish to be visible on the web into your www directory. Your home page should be named index.html (or index.htm), but you may have as many pages with as many different names as you like, so long as you do not exceed the 100 MB disk space limit for your account.

Each page will have a different URL. Your home page can be found at http://www.grex.org/~youraccount/ and any other page can be found at http://www.grex.org/~youraccount/filename.

For links between the pages of your site, it is best to use relative links in your hypertext links. This means you should not link to a file using the full URL, like this: <a href="http://www.grex.org/~youraccount/filename">, but rather you should use the much simpler form <a href=filename>. Of course you must use the full link in a pointer from another site.

Return to the table of contents

Why can't I find my page when I look from the net?

There are three possible problems:

You didn't put it in your www directory.

If you use lynx on Grex, you can view any page with it that you have read access to. That is because lynx is reading the page directly. If you try to access the page via Grex's web server, the page must be located in the www directory or it will not be visible.

You are not using the proper URL for your page.

If a page named foo.html is in your www directory, its full path is ~youraccount/www/foo.html, but the URL for it has no "www" because it is assumed by the web server that files must be in the www directory. So its URL would be http://www.grex.org/~youraccount/foo.html.

URLs of the form http://www.grex.org/a/y/o/youraccount/www/foo.html do not work.

Your permissions are not correct.

If you have changed the permissions on either your home directory or your www directory to "700", the web server will not be able to see your files. Both your home directory and www directory must have at least the "x" bit set, or your pages will not be visible on the web. Use permissions of "711" on each directory if you do not wish to allow other people to see what files are there, and use "755" if you do. "700" will render your files inaccessible.

Return to the table of contents

Why can't I edit my page using the "e" command in Lynx?

There are two possible problems:

You must specify to lynx which editor you want to use. You do this by typing the "o" command to bring up the options page, then select "editor" and specify which unix editor you want to use (examples, pico, vi, joe, emacs).
You must be accessing the page you want to edit locally, and not through the web server. Lynx cannot edit pages it fetches through the web server. Thus, if you are pointing to the page with an http URL, you will not be able to edit it. You can solve this problem by starting lynx with an argument on the linend (for example lynx www/index.html) or by using a local file URL (for example, type the "g" command in lynx, and specify file://localhost/a/y/o/youraccount/www/index.html to bring up your page. If your page has a file: URL, it will be editable in lynx. You can save this URL in your bookmarks file so you do not have to type it in each time.

Return to the table of contents

How can I put my pages on Grex if I make them on my computer?

If you are connecting to Grex from the internet, you should use ftp to transfer your file to Grex. If you have a direct internet connection, you should be able to run an ftp client on your PC. If you are dialing into a remote host to gain access to the net, you must first transfer your files to your host system using a file transfer protocol supported by your terminal emulator software, and then use ftp to move them from there to your grex account.

Remember to log into grex with your account and password. Grex does not support anonymous ftp.

Also remember to put the files into your www directory, not your home directory.

If you dial into grex directly, use a file transfer protocol such as sz or kermit to move the files to your www directory.

Return to the table of contents

Can I have HTML Forms on my page?

In order to support HTML forms, you must provide a CGI script or program to process the form. Grex's web server does not support CGI programs written by Grex users if they consume lots of CPU time. Therefore the only way you could have a form on your Grex page is if it is pointed to a cgi program on some other server, or if it is written in such a way as to reduce the work our CPUs have to do; write your CGI in such a way that the process exits and make sure it cannot be misused by other Grex users. Without that, the answer is no.

Return to the table of contents

How do I get my page listed in the Grex Users directory?

If you have pages on Grex which are correctly set up and visible on the internet, You just have to write mail to webmaster@grex.org and ask to be listed.

Return to the table of contents

If I have a page elsewhere, can I be listed on Grex?

Yes, as long as you maintain a Grex account, you are a Grex user. Just send mail to webmaster@grex.org, requesting this. Be sure to include the URL you wish it point to.

Return to the table of contents

How do I know how many "hits" my page is getting?

Grex's web server keeps statistics. This information is published weekly, and it contains hit counts for all user pages with 10 or more hits per week. Look on the statistics page.

Information is only available in summary form. The detail records in the log file are not published or available.

Return to the table of contents

How can I put a counter on my page?

The answer to this question keeps changing. Have a look at the Yahoo directory of free web counters. You should be able to use one of the counters described there on your Grex web pages without violating any rules.

Return to the table of contents

Can I put links to conference items on my page?

Yes, if you want to put a pointer to your favorite Grex item or conference on your web page, you can do it. A link to the Agora conference would have the URL:

https://grex.org/cgi-bin/backtalk/peek%3Aagora%3A2

Just replace the name Agora with whatever conference you want to link to.

This will put anyone who clicks it into the conference via Backtalk. They will be in read-only mode, so people without Grex accounts will be able to look at the conference. If they are using a non-graphical browser like lynx, it will put them in the vanilla interface. Otherwise the pistachio interface is used.

You can also link to a specific item in a conference. Below is the URL for a link to item 2 in the agora conference:

https://grex.org/cgi-bin/backtalk/peek%3Aagora%3A2

Or you can link to a specific response to a specific item. Here is a link to response 8 of item 1 in the agora conference:

https://grex.org/cgi-bin/backtalk/peek%3Aagora%3A1%3A8

You can also link to ranges of responses. The following URL links to responses 0 (that's the item text), 3, and 7 through 12 of item one of the agora conference:

https://grex.org/cgi-bin/backtalk/peek%3Aagora%3A1%3A0,3,7-12

Return to the table of contents

Help, I forgot my Grex password!

For issues that aren't specificly related to the web or Grex's web server, you would be much better off sending mail to help@grex.org, instead of webmaster. While a Webmaster can probably help you out, or answer your questions, there are many more staffers reading the staff mailbox.. So mail sent to staff is more likely to be read and answered quickly than mail sent to webmaster.

Return to the table of contents

$Id: wwwfaq.xhtml 1548 2016-09-25 15:09:10Z kentn $ We welcome your feedback.